<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-07T18:28:42+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Frederik K. Ciupek and central hub for research, projects, and blog posts. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Vanna Tailwind and the Gamma-Volatility Feedback Loop</title><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/vanna-tailwinds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vanna Tailwind and the Gamma-Volatility Feedback Loop"/><published>2025-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/vanna-tailwinds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/vanna-tailwinds/"><![CDATA[<p>Me and many people following the market are very confused by whats going on right now. The market is up more than 15% since liberation day, volatility is down and we do not understand really why. Even at its best with all the trade deals in place, the minimum tariffs are going to be somewhere around 10% which should at least SOMEWHAT depress the stock market.</p> <p>Reading Bloomberg this morning I came across an interesting article talking about the VIX that I would like to share here. The CBOE Volatility Index (VIX), often called the “fear index” or “Wall Street’s fear gauge,” is a measure of market expectations for stock market volatility over the next 30 days. It’s derived from the prices of S&amp;P 500 index options and reflects how much market turbulence investors anticipate. A higher VIX typically indicates more fear or uncertainty, while a lower VIX suggests more stability. It is a measure of average implied volatility for the S&amp;P over the next 30 days.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-07/vix-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-07/vix-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-07/vix-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-07/vix.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="VIX as of June 7th 2025" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>From our option courses we might still remember something called <strong>implied volatility</strong> and the relationship between option prices and volatility overall captured by the option greek <em>vega</em>. But here is a quick reminder:</p> <h4 id="what-is-implied-volatility">What is Implied Volatility?</h4> <p><strong>Implied volatility (IV)</strong> represents the market’s forecast of a likely movement in a security’s price. Rather than being observed directly, it is <strong>backed out</strong> of the market price of an option using an option pricing model like <strong>Black-Scholes</strong>.</p> <p>In short, it’s the volatility that makes the <strong>model price = market price</strong>. The market price (again in a fully rational world, otherwise only a VERY good approximation) with the <strong>Black-Scholes-Merton formula</strong> which is given by:</p> <p>$ C = S_0 \cdot N(d_1) - K e^{-rT} \cdot N(d_2) $</p> <p>Where:</p> <ul> <li>$ C $ = Call option price</li> <li>$ S_0 $ = Current stock price</li> <li>$ K $ = Strike price</li> <li>$ r $ = Risk-free interest rate</li> <li>$ T $ = Time to expiration (in years)</li> <li>$ \sigma $ = Volatility of the underlying asset</li> <li>$ N(\cdot) $ = Cumulative distribution function of the standard normal distribution</li> </ul> <p>And:</p> \[d_1 = \frac{\ln(S_0 / K) + (r + \frac{\sigma^2}{2})T}{\sigma \sqrt{T}}, \quad d_2 = d_1 - \sigma \sqrt{T}\] <p>The implied volatility of an option is the $\sigma$ needed for the price to equal the rest of the inputs which are all known. What does the option price have to do with the volatility though? Well, an option is (if you delta hedge it correctly) just a bet on volatility since you make money holding the option by selling the underlying when you are up and buying when the underlying moves down. This is often referred to as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convexity_(finance)"> positive convexity </a>. Whether you buy or sell an option is then just a function of you thinking that implied volatility of the option is higher/lower than it should be.</p> <p>How volatility overall affects option prices is captured by a <strong>Vega</strong>. One of many option “Greeks” it measures the sensitivity of the option price to a changes in <strong>volatility</strong>:</p> \[\text{Vega} = \frac{\partial C}{\partial \sigma}\] <h4 id="why-is-vega-important">Why is Vega Important?</h4> <p>Traders often watch vega to understand how their portfolios might react to a change in implied volatility. If you’re holding long options in a low-volatility environment, increasing IV can significantly boost the value of your position.</p> <p>When implied volatility falls, option prices drop. This not only affects valuations—it also structurally now changes the delta hedging flows in the market.</p> <p>At the heart of this dynamic lies another option greek less often talked about <strong>vanna</strong>, the sensitivity of delta to volatility changes, formally defined as $∂Δ / ∂σ$. You can read more about <a href="https://quantra.quantinsti.com/glossary/Vanna "> vanna here.</a> It is an extension of the vega measure so to speak.</p> <p>How does vanna impact calls and puts?</p> <ul> <li><strong>Calls</strong>: Vanna is positive. Long call holders are typically short the underlying for <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/deltahedging.asp#:~:text=Delta%20hedging%20is%20a%20trading,of%20stock%20or%20ETF%20shares. "> delta-hedging.</a> As implied volatility drops, the option price falls. With the option price falling the option’s delta also falls, so hedgers must buy back the underlying—creating <strong>buying pressure</strong>.</li> <li><strong>Puts</strong>: Vanna is negative. Long put holders are long the underlying to hedge. As vol drops, the delta approaches zero, so hedgers must sell—creating <strong>selling pressure</strong>.</li> </ul> <p>But here’s the twist: most dealers are short puts, because clients seek downside protection. So, the <strong>signs flip</strong>.</p> <ul> <li>Dealers short puts = short the underlying for delta-neutrality = positive vanna (As vol drops, the delta increases, pushing it up from negative to 0)</li> </ul> <p>So, as implied volatility drops, the delta of those short puts shrinks → <strong>dealers cover their shorts</strong> → <strong>buying pressure on equities</strong>.</p> <p>This is what’s referred to as the <strong>“vanna tailwind.”</strong>. Especially into the weekends traders do not want want to carry risk since the market is closed and they cant hedge during that time. This leads to a recurring bid under markets as dealers buy to hedge their net short put exposure.</p> <h4 id="gamma-and-mean-reversion">Gamma and Mean-Reversion</h4> <p>This vanna effect doesn’t act alone. Dealers are typically <strong>short gamma</strong>, particularly from selling puts as fat-tail insurance to their clients. Gamma ($Γ$) captures how delta shifts as the underlying price changes: \(\text{Γ} = \frac{\partial Δ}{\partial S}\)</p> <p>Because dealers are mostly short the options to clients that want downside protection their trades have negative convexity. That means that they are short a positive gamma position.</p> <p><strong>Positive gamma positions</strong> (e.g. long straddles or clients buying gamma synthetically) mean that as the underlying moves up or down, the option’s delta moves in the direction of the move:</p> <ul> <li>If the stock pops, you become more long the stock.</li> <li>If it drops, you become more short the stock</li> </ul> <p>This positive gamma risk is carried by dealers who, to remain delta neutral, must dynamically delta hedge their positioning. Let us take the example of a short put option again:</p> <p>They are short the contract, have a positive delta exposure which they need to neutralize by selling the underlying (delta hedging) and are short gamma. When the market rallies, the dealer’s short gamma book need to sell the underlying stock to bring their delta back to zero. When the market falls, they do the opposite: buy stock to offset the new short-delta.</p> <p>Because the dealer is selling into strength and buying into weakness, these hedging flows <em>dampen price moves</em> through counter cyclical trading. These dealers injects liquidity not the market that suppress realized volatility of the index (often called ‘mean reverting behavior’) which in turn reduces implied volatility since there are less expected movements in the market, in turn lowering the VIX. A lower VIX brings us back to the vanna tailwinds mentioned above depressing option values through Vega in a positive feedback loop depressing the VIX even further.</p> <h4 id="structural-implications-vol-control--risk-parity">Structural Implications: Vol-Control &amp; Risk Parity</h4> <p>There is another affect that might be increasing risky assets (especially the S&amp;P) as a result of the volatility crash. The recent global decline in volatility also activated <strong>volatility targeting funds</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>These funds aim to maintain a constant portfolio volatility.</li> <li>As vol drops, they must <strong>increase leverage</strong> to hit their target vol so they <strong>buy futures, ETFs, equities</strong>.</li> <li>This boosts upward momentum initiated by vanna and gamma flows and amplifies them</li> </ul> <p>However, this leverage buildup has a dark side: when vol spikes again, these same models will <strong>de-lever</strong>, selling the assets they just bought. This could make future drawdowns sharper.</p> <p>This is just one way we can think about how the volatility crash since Liberation Day might have impacted risky assets and - while maybe not inflated - led to large gains in equities. Since derivatives are already a market bigger than the underlying themselves it might stand to reason that the effect is not negligible. When volatility spikes, we might see a sharpe decline resulting from volatility control fund and risk parity funds.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="markets"/><category term="options"/><category term="volatility"/><category term="vanna"/><category term="gamma"/><category term="market microstructure"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How falling implied volatility creates structural equity buying demand through option market dynamics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">May 2025 Non‐Farm Payrolls - Stronger Hiring Boosts Cash Flow Expectations Despite Lower Rate‐Cut Odds</title><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/non-farm-may2025/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="May 2025 Non‐Farm Payrolls - Stronger Hiring Boosts Cash Flow Expectations Despite Lower Rate‐Cut Odds"/><published>2025-06-06T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-06T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/non-farm-may2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/non-farm-may2025/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.bls.gov/news.release/empsit.nr0.htm"> Labor Department’s non‐farm payroll report </a> , released on June 6, 2025, showed that U.S. employers added 139,000 new jobs in May, surpassing Wall Street’s expectation of 124,000. This figure, while signaling a slight slowdown from April’s 165,000 gain, still came in well above consensus.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-06/nfp_may2025-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-06/nfp_may2025-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-06/nfp_may2025-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-06/nfp_may2025.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Non-farm Numbers May 2025" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="caption"> May 2025 non‐farm payrolls showed 139,000 jobs added, above the 124,000 consensus estimate </div> <p>Despite the headline that U.S. hiring slowed relative to April through the ADA report that sent stocks higher and yields down, <a hre="">f=”hhttps://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/labour-market-weakning/”&gt; which I talked about in my latest blog post </a>, the beat versus expectations sent stocks higher on the day (June 6th).</p> <p>At first glance, one might expect stronger job gains to push markets lower—if markets anticipate fewer rate cuts, the discount rate used in equity valuation edges up, which should depress valuations. Yet equities rallied. To understand why, it helps to break down stock valuation into its two core components:</p> <ul> <li>Expected Cash Flows</li> <li>Discount Rate</li> </ul> <div align="center"> $$ V_0 = \sum_{t=1}^{N} \frac{CF_t}{(1 + r)^t} $$ </div> <p>where:</p> <ul> <li>$V_0$ is the value of stock $i$ in time $t=0$</li> <li>$CF_t$ is the expected cash flow at time $t$</li> <li>$r$ is the appropriate discount rate</li> <li>$N$ is the forecast horizon</li> </ul> <h3 id="expected-cash-flows">Expected Cash Flows</h3> <p>At its simplest, a stock’s value is the present value of all future cash flows a company is expected to generate. When the labor market is resilient—even if it’s not scorching hot—corporate revenue and earnings forecasts generally rise, as stronger hiring suggests consumers are employed, spending remains solid, and business activity holds up. In May, the 139,000‐job gain, beating expectations by about 10%, painted a picture of an economy still chugging along, tempering fears of an imminent slowdown</p> <h4 id="consumer-spending-and-corporate-revenues">Consumer Spending and Corporate Revenues</h4> <p>With payroll gains above forecasts, analysts (the market as a whole) raised their projections for consumer spending growth over the next few quarters. Consumer sentiment is also for the first time in 4 months holding steady at 52.2 according to the<a href="https://www.sca.isr.umich.edu/"> University of Michigan Sentiment survey</a> (sentiment is still down 25% YoY however). Retailers, restaurants, and service‐sector firms tend to see topline upside when households feel confident about employment. As a result, consensus S&amp;P 500 earnings forecasts for 2025 and 2026 ticked higher in the hours after the report. Even a modest 1–2% upward revision in aggregate earnings projections can translate into meaningful increases in the sum‐of‐discounted cash‐flows for the index.</p> <p>Taken together, these factors mean that the expected free cash flows embedded in equity valuations moved upward by more than any corresponding increase in discount‐rate assumptions (as detailed below).</p> <ol> <li>Discount Rate The discount rate in equity valuation models—often proxied by the risk‐free Treasury yield plus an equity risk premium—reflects market expectations for the Federal Reserve’s policy rate path.</li> </ol> <h4 id="ratecut-probability-falls">Rate‐Cut Probability Falls</h4> <p>Heading into the May report, futures markets priced in roughly a 20% probability of 2-3 25 basis‐point Fed cut by September 2025, 54% change of 1-2 and only a 25% chance of them holding to their current target rate of 425-450 bps. After the stronger‐than‐expected payrolls, that probability fell to around 9.4% for a 2-3 25 basis points cut, an unchanged probability of a 1-2 25bps cut and a much higher 35% change of no cuts — implying markets now expect rates to stay higher for longer. In isolation, this raises the present‐value discount factor, pushing down valuations.</p> <h4 id="10-year-treasury-yields-tick-higher">10-Year Treasury Yields Tick Higher</h4> <p>On report day, the 10-year Treasury yield rose from 4.3% to around 4.45% a s bond investors repriced Fed‐funds outlooks. If we translate that move into a higher discount rate—say, adding 15 bps to the forward yield curve assumptions in a discounted cash flow model—it would shave a few percentage points off of valuation multiples, all else equal.</p> <p>However, in this case, the lift to cash‐flow forecasts (via stronger revenue and modest margin revisions) more than offset the slight upward revision in discount‐rate assumptions. The net effect: a higher present‐value of future cash flows, which sent stocks modestly higher on the day.</p> <h2 id="putting-it-all-together-why-stocks-are-up">Putting It All Together: Why Stocks Are Up</h2> <p>Stronger Job Gains → Higher Cash‐Flow Projections</p> <p>Rate‐Cut Odds Dip → Slightly Higher Discount Rate</p> <p>Futures pricing shifted to imply rates will remain near current levels at least through mid‐2025, raising the discount factor by about 10-15 bps on the long end.</p> <p>On a DCF basis, that would modestly trim valuations—everything else held equal.</p> <p><strong>Net Effect</strong>: Cash‐Flow Lift &gt; Discount‐Rate Drag</p> <h2 id="note-market-psychology-and-positioning">Note: Market Psychology and Positioning</h2> <p>This all only holds in rational markets which we do not operate in. Many investors had already positioned for “bad news = good news,” expecting a downshift in hiring that would turbo‐charge rate‐cut expectations. Instead, the actual stronger print caught some funds off‐guard, spurring short‐covering and tactical buying in growth names, maybe overoptimistic buying.</p> <p>What Comes Next? I will be watching two things</p> <ol> <li> <p>Fed Speak and Forward Guidance: Even as payrolls hold up, the Fed’s communications on inflation and labor‐market slack remain key. If Fed officials lean more hawkish in speeches—emphasizing data dependency—the discount rate could move further upward.</p> </li> <li> <p>Earnings Season Preview: With Q2 corporate results due in July, investors will test whether companies can deliver on the higher cash‐flow projections implied by today’s jobs data. Earnings beats would reinforce current valuation levels; disappointments could quickly reverse the modest rally.</p> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="economics"/><category term="labor market"/><category term="interest rates"/><category term="stock valuation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[U.S. hiring added 139,000 jobs in May—beating forecasts—keeping rate‐cut odds lower, yet stocks are climbing as cash‐flow forecasts get a lift that outweighs a slightly higher discount rate.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ADA Employment Report points to strongly weakening Labour market</title><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/labour-market-weakning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ADA Employment Report points to strongly weakening Labour market"/><published>2025-06-04T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-04T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/labour-market-weakning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/labour-market-weakning/"><![CDATA[<p>The Job data released on June 4th 2025shows that just <a href="https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/stock-market-today-trump-tariffs-trade-war-06-04-2025/card/u-s-hiring-slows-again-adp-report-shows-lk7TGwCNs0lm1cUP5LNP">37,000 jobs were created in May,</a> down almost 50% from 62,000 in April according to the ADP National Employment report released Wednesday.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-04/adp_job_report-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-04/adp_job_report-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-04/adp_job_report-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2025-06-04/adp_job_report.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="ADP Job Report May 2025" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> This figure highlights the ADP National Employment report for May 2025, showcasing the significant drop in job creation compared to April and the weakest in more than two years. </div> <p>This severely undershot expectations of 110,000 new jobs for May. The ADP National Employment Report, jointly developed with the Stanford Digital Economy Lab, has been published ahead of the more comprehensive report due Friday the 6th of June by the Labor Department’s Bureau of Labor Statistics. Reuters claims that these reports are uncorrelated. Government data released for April showed that Job openings increased to 191,000 to 7.391 million and Layoffs jump 196,000 - the biggest rise in nine months but still remain low despite market uncertainty and there were 1.03 job openings for every unemployed person. Hiring only rises to 169,000. People quitting their jobs shown in orange in the interactive graph below declined by the most since last November declining by 4.5% (November 2024 5%). The measure of people quitting their job is a proxy for consumer and labor market confidence.</p> <p>This newest ADA data thus is supporting the understanding of ebbing confidence in the labor market.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-4"> <iframe src="/assets/html/jolts.html" width="120%" height="700" frameborder="0" loading="lazy"> </iframe> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Interactive chart comparing Job Openings &amp; Hire and Quits &amp; Layoffs/Discharges </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-4"> <iframe src="/assets/html/jolts_percentage_change.html" width="120%" height="700" frameborder="0" loading="lazy"> </iframe> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Interactive chart comparing Job Openings &amp; Hire and Quits &amp; Layoffs/Discharges in % changes </div> <p>The market rose higher between 0.2% and 0.3% and the 10-year TY fell from 4.46% to 4.38% (2% change) as the market is pricing in interest rate cuts in the future. I am very excited for this Friday’s nonfarm job report numbers since I believe the 37,000 to be a bit low. But I do believe there is going to be a negative surprise.</p> <p>To see exactly how much the market is pricing in rate cuts this year we can have a closer look at the <a href="https://www.cmegroup.com/markets/interest-rates/cme-fedwatch-tool.html">probabilities assigned to rate cuts by the market</a>. The the next FOMC meeting 13 days away (June 18th) the market is pricing in a 4% probability of a 25bps rate cut in June.</p> <p>You can also check out my <a href="https://www.cmegroup.com/markets/interest-rates/cme-fedwatch-tool.html"> github repository </a> or my writeup on my <a href="frederikciupek.github.io/projects/fedwatch"> website </a> for a full replication of this method for June (although my results are not the exact same which I am going to troubleshoot).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="economics"/><category term="labour market"/><category term="interest rates"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Slowest job growth in over two years in May 2025 contrasting other indications of a robust job market. Are we going to see a rate cut any time soon?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revisiting Bryan Kelly’s GARCH Model</title><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/revisiting-ML/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revisiting Bryan Kelly’s GARCH Model"/><published>2025-06-02T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/revisiting-ML</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2025/revisiting-ML/"><![CDATA[<p>GARCH Modeling</p> <p>This theme implements a built-in Jekyll feature, the use of Rouge, for syntax highlighting. It supports more than 100 languages. This example is in Python All you have to do is wrap your code in markdown code tags:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">python
</span><span class="n">code</span> <span class="n">code</span> <span class="n">code</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">int</span> <span class="n">argc</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">char</span> <span class="n">const</span> \<span class="o">*</span><span class="n">argv</span><span class="p">[])</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">string</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="n">cout</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">input a string: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nf">getline</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">cin</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nb">int</span> <span class="n">length</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">length</span><span class="p">();</span>

    <span class="n">char</span> <span class="n">charArray</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">new</span> <span class="n">char</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">[</span><span class="n">length</span><span class="p">];</span>

    <span class="n">charArray</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">myString</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nf">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">int</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">length</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">++</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">){</span>
        <span class="n">cout</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="n">charArray</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s"> </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="quant-finance"/><category term="volatility modeling"/><category term="forecasting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this post I revisit some of volatility modeling with GARCH to not forget the theory and coding associated with it. In particular I will be looking at a GARCH model and in the future revisit the DCC GARCH model.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024[[read-time]] min read We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://frederikciupek.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[<h3>External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</h3> <p>If you prefer publishing blog posts on medium.com or other external sources, starting version v0.5.0, <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">al-folio</a> lets you to display your external posts in the blog feed of your website! 🎉🎉</p> <p>Configuring external sources of super simple. After upgrading to v0.5.0, just add the following section to your _config.yml:</p> <pre>external_sources:<br />  - name: medium.com  # name of the source (arbitrary string)<br />    rss_url: <a href="https://medium.com/@al-folio/feed">https://medium.com/@&lt;your-medium-username&gt;/feed</a></pre> <p>The example above adds your medium.com blog post feed as an external source. But you can add arbitrary RSS feeds as sources.</p> <p>Any questions or suggestions? 👉 Start <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/discussions">a discussion on GitHub</a>!</p> <p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;postId=b60a1d241a0a" width="1" height="1" alt=""/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>